Higher School of Modern Mathematics
Moscow Institute of Physics and Technology
(National Research University)
9 Institutsky lane
Dolgoprudny, Moscow region 141701
Russia

☐ +7 903 1253191
☑ koziakin.vs@mipt.ru
⑥ kozyakin.github.io
⑥ 0000-0002-6465-0040
☑ Victor\_Kozyakin
⑧ QuhA8hoAAAAJ
☑ kozyakin v 1



# Victor Kozyakin

#### Personal Information

Date of Birth April 16, 1950

Place of Birth Gorkii, USSR

Nationality Russian

Marital Status Married

## Education

1967–1972 M.Sc. in Mathematics, Voronezh State University, Mathematical Faculty, Voronezh (Russia)

1973–1976 **Ph.D.**, Institute for Control Problems, Academy of Sciences of the USSR, Moscow (Russia)

## Degrees

degree Doctor of Physical and Mathematical Sciences (Dr.Sc.)

year 1992

institution National Research Institute of System Studies, Moscow, Russia

thesis Methods of stability analysis of desynchronized impulse systems

degree Candidate of Physical and Mathematical Sciences (Ph.D.)

supervisor Prof. M.A. Krasnosel'skii

year 1979

institution Institute of Electronic Technology, Moscow, Russia

thesis Some problems of the theory of bifurcations of periodic motions (phenomenon of subfurcation)

#### Scientific Interests

- Systems analysis (control theory, discrete event systems theory, desynchronized systems, mathematical modeling)
- o Nonlinear analysis and its applications, bifurcation theory
- Linear functional analysis
- o Qualitative problems of differential equations and operator equations
- Influence of temporal/spatial discretization on the behavior of continuous dynamical systems
- o Investigation of the joint/generalized spectral radius for a set of linear operators

#### Scientific Grants

Executive in charge RFBR (Russian Foundation for Basic Research) Grants 93-01-00884, 96-15-96048, 97-

 $01\text{-}00692, \, 99\text{-}01\text{-}00333, \, 00\text{-}15\text{-}96116, \, 03\text{-}01\text{-}00258, \, 04\text{-}01\text{-}00330, \, 06\text{-}01\text{-}00256, \, 06\text{-}01\text{-}72552, \, 09\text{-}01\text{-}00119, \, 10\text{-}01\text{-}00175, \, 10\text{-}01\text{-}93112, \, 13\text{-}01\text{-}13105, \, 14\text{-}50\text{-}00150$ 

Executive in charge Grant of the President of the Russian Federation "Scientific Schools" 1532.2003.1

Executive RSF (Russian Science Foundation) Grant 16-11-00063, 2016-2018

Executive Australian Research Council Grants A 8913 2609 and A 6953 2878, 1993–1997

Executive DFG Forschungschwerpunkt "Ergodentheorie, Analysis und effiziente Simulation dynamischer Systeme" (Germany), 1999–2000

Executive CRG-961115 "Computational complexity of control problems" (France), 2001

## International Cooperation

1993–1997 six (or seven?) 2-month visits as Associate Researcher at Queensland University, Brisbane, Australia, and Deakin University, Geelong, within Australian Research Counsel grants A 8913 2609 and A 6953 2878 headed by Prof. Peter Kloeden and Prof. Phil Diamond

1994, 1997 2-weeks visits as Visiting Academician at Laboratory for Parallel Computing, Federal University of Rio de Janeiro, Brazil. Visits organized by Prof. Eugenius Kaszkurewicz and Prof. Amit Bhaya

1999 1-month visit as "Professeur invité" at University of Rouen, France. Visit organized by Prof. Claude Dellacherie

1999, 2000 three 3-month visits at Johann Wolfgang Goethe University, Frankfurt am Main, Germany, within DFG Grant "Ergodentheorie, Analysis und effiziente Simulation dynamischer Systeme" headed by Prof. Peter Kloeden and Prof. Björn Schmalfuß

2001 2-week visit at VERIMAG (Grenoble, France) within NATO grant CRG-961115 "Computational complexity of control problems". Visit organized by Prof. Vincent Blondel and Prof. Evgueni Assarine

2003 2-month visit of both Boole Centre for Research in Informatics and Department of Applied Mathematics, University College Cork. Visit organized by Prof. Patrick Fitzpatrick and Prof. Alexei Pokrovskii

2005 1-month visit of Weierstraß-Institut für Angewandte Analysis und Stochastik, Berlin. Visit organized by Prof. Dmitri Ratchinski

2011, 2014 1-week visits to the Nanjing University and the Sun Yat-Sen (Zhongshan) University, China. Organizer of the visit: prof. Xiongping Dai

#### Scientific Activities

2003-now Member of the International Society of Difference Equations (http://www.isdeds.com)

2001-2024 Member of the Editorial Board of the electronic journal  $Information\ Processes\ (http://www.jip.ru)$ 

2011-2022 Member of the Editorial Board of the journal Discrete Dynamics in Nature and Society (https://www.hindawi.com/journals/ddns/)

1996-2000 Member of the Dissertation Soviet K.064.12.04 (scientific degree's qualification board) at the Yaroslavl State University

2001-2022 Member of the Dissertation Soviet D.002.077.01 (scientific degree's qualification board) at the Institute for Information Transmission Problems

2011-2022 Member of the Dissertation Soviet D.002.077.03 (scientific degree's qualification board) at the Institute for Information Transmission Problems

## Reviewing

V. Kozyakn has reviewed articles submitted to the following journals: Abstract and Applied Analysis; Automatica; Computer Systems Science and Engineering; Discrete and Continuous Dynamical Systems - B; Dynamical Systems: An International Journal; Foundations of Computational Mathematics; Fundamenta Mathematicae; IEEE Transactions on Automatic Control; IEEE Transactions on Circuits and Systems; IEEE Transactions on Neural Networks; Journal of Applied Mathematics and Physics; Journal of Difference Equations and Applications; Journal of Function Spaces; Journal of Mathematical Analysis and Applications; Journal of the Australian Mathematical Society; Journal of the European Mathematical Society; Linear Algebra and its Applications; Linear and Multilinear Algebra; Mathematics and Computers in Simulation; Mathematics of Control, Signals, and Systems; Mathematische Nachrichten; Methodology and Computing in Applied Probability; Nonlinear Analysis, Theory, Methods and Applications; Nonlinear Control Systems; Nonlinearity; Numerical Algorithms; Opuscula Mathematica; Proceedings of the London Mathematical Society; SIAM Journal on Control and Optimization; SIAM Journal on Matrix Analysis and Applications; Systems & Control Letters; Transactions of the American Mathematical Society.

## Employment History

Aug. 2024-now

Higher School of Modern Mathematics, Moscow Institute of Physics and Technology (National Research University). Principal Researcher. Description of work: study of the generalized spectral radius of a family of linear operators.

1990-Aug. 2024

Institute for Information Transmission Problems. Russian Academy of Sciences. Senior Researcher, Leading Researcher, Principal Researcher, Deputy Head of the Sector of Mathematical Methods in the Control Theory. Description of work: study of stability of asynchronous systems. Introduced new notions of stability in classes of desynchronization and developed methods for studying the stability of asynchronous systems. Investigation of the influence of controllability-type on transients in asynchronous systems. Applications of the stability theory of asynchronous systems to the analysis of the dynamics of datagram networks. Investigation of the influence of temporal/spatial discretization on the dynamics of continuous systems. Study of the stability of asynchronous Hopfield-Tank neural networks. Investigation of the problem of generalized spectral radius of a family of linear operators.

- 1992–1993 Hebrew State University. Faculty of Computer Science. Moscow. Associate Professor. Work description: lectures in linear algebra and geometry. Supervision of students.
- 1988–1990 Research Institute of Control Problems, "NPO ASU Moskva" of the Moscow City Executive Committee. Senior Researcher. Work description: study of stability of phase and frequency desynchronized systems. Development of symbolic dynamics technique for studying stability of frequency desynchronized systems. Modeling of air pollution in the Moscow region.

National Cardiology Research Center. Russian Academy of Medical Sciences, Moscow. Senior Engineer, Junior Researcher, Senior Researcher, Leading Researcher, Head of the Group of Computer Real-time Diagnostics of Cardiac Rhythm in Coronary Care Units, Head of the Group of Image Processing. Work description: estimation of electrocardiogram parameters. Development of an automated computer system for real-time diagnosis in coronary care units. Development of new algorithms for fast smoothing of electrocardiograms and fast removal of artifacts, based on the principle of "median filtering". Development of reliable algorithms based on median filtering for determination of wave parameters of electrocardiogram (QRS-complexes and P-wave) and for edge detection in radioisotope images. Topological classification of singularities. New necessary and sufficient conditions for topological classification of singularities for sub-definite mappings. Application of the developed methods to the study of the Hopf bifurcation problem.

- 1973–1976 Institute for Control Problems. Academy of Sciences of the USSR, Moscow. Postgraduate student. Thesis description: study of bifurcation effects accompanying the loss of equilibrium of autonomous/periodic differential/difference equations. It was found that the loss of stability is generally accompanied by the bifurcation of long periodic solutions whose periods grow to infinity at the moment of bifurcation. This phenomenon was called the phenomenon of subfurcation. Later, the simple explanation of the phenomenon of subfurcation was given by V. Arnold (but only for a sufficiently smooth case).
- 1972–1973 Institute of Mathematics of the Voronezh State University, Voronezh. Engineer. Description of the work: analysis of vibrostability conditions for 2nd order differential equations.

## Brief Biography

Victor Kozyakin was born in 1950 in the city of Gorky (now Nizhny Novgorod), USSR. He studied mathematics at Voronezh State University (USSR), and then specialized as a post graduate at the Institute of Control Sciences of the USSR Academy of Sciences.

Received a Ph.D. in physics and mathematics from the Institute of Electronic Technology in Moscow (USSR), and a Doctor of Science in mathematics (Doctor of Physics and Mathematics) from the National Research Institute for Systems Studies in Moscow (USSR) in 1979 and 1991, respectively.

From 1976 V. Kozyakin has been working at the National Cardiology Research Center, Russian Academy of Medical Sciences, in Moscow. He was a senior engineer, junior research fellow, senior research fellow, leading research fellow, head of the real-time computer diagnostics group for cardiac arrhythmias in the intensive care unit, head of the imaging group in the radioisotope research laboratory.

From 1988 to 1990 V. Kozyakin has been a senior researcher at the Research Institute of Control Problems ("NPO ASU Moscow").

From 1990 to August 2024 V. Kozyakin has been working at the Institute of Information Transmission Problems of the Russian Academy of Sciences, Moscow (Russia). During this time he held the positions of senior researcher, leading researcher, principal researcher and deputy head of the sector of mathematical methods of control theory. His main scientific interest during this period was the study of the stability of asynchronous systems. His interests also include the study of stability in various classes of desynchronization, the study of the influence of controllability type properties on transient processes in asynchronous systems, applications of the theory of stability of asynchronous systems to the analysis of the dynamics of data transmission networks, the study of the effect of temporal/spatial discretization on the dynamics of continuous systems, the study of the stability of asynchronous neural networks. Recently, he has studied the joint/generalized spectral radius problem for a family of linear operators. V. Kozyakin is co-author of 3 monographs, about 200 articles and

From August 2024, he has been working at the Higher School of Modern Mathematics at MIPT and is engaged in the further development of the theory of joint/generalized spectral radius for a family of linear operators.

V. Kozyakin is the author of 3 monographs, about 200 articles and conference reports.

## Monographs

N.A. Bobylev, V.G. Boltyanskii, S.Yu. Vsekhsvyatskii, V.V. Kalashnikov, V.S. Kozyakin, V.B. Kolmanovskii, A.A. Kravchenko, A.M. Krasnosel'skii, A.V. Pokrovskii, *Mathematical systems theory*, Moscow, Nauka, 1986, 166 pp. (in Russian)

E.A. Asarin, V.S. Kozyakin, M.A. Krasnosel'skii, N.A. Kuznetsov, *Analysis of the stability of asynchronous discrete systems*, Moscow, Nauka, 1992, 408 pp. (in Russian)

P. Diamond, P. Kloeden, V. Kozyakin, A. Pokrovskii, *Semi-hyperbolicity and bi-shadowing*, American Institute of Mathematical Sciences, 2012. Vol. 1 of AIMS Series on Random and Computational Dynamics. xvi+217 pp.

Full list of publications (about 200) see at https://kozyakin.github.io/en/publications. Selected publications are cited below.

### Selected Publications

- V. Kozyakin, Non-Sturmian sequences of matrices providing the maximum growth rate of matrix products, Automatica J. IFAC, 145 (2022), Paper No. 110574, 10, doi:10. 1016/j.automatica.2022.110574, URL https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0005109822004356, arXiv:2112.00391.
- V. Kozyakin, Minimax joint spectral radius and stabilizability of discrete-time linear switching control systems, Discrete Contin. Dyn. Syst. Ser. B, 24 (2019), 3537-3556, doi:10.3934/dcdsb.2018277, URL https://aimsciences.org/article/doi/10.3934/dcdsb.2018277, arXiv:1712.06805.
- V. Kozyakin, Hourglass alternative and the finiteness conjecture for the spectral characteristics of sets of non-negative matrices, Linear Algebra Appl., 489 (2016), 167–185, doi:10.1016/j.laa.2015.10.017, URL https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0024379515006126, arXiv:1507.00492.
- E. Asarin, J. Cervelle, A. Degorre et al., Entropy games and matrix multiplication games, in: 33rd Symposium on Theoretical Aspects of Computer Science, (STACS 2016), (eds.) N. Ollinger and H. Vollmer, vol. 47 of LIPIcs. Leibniz Int. Proc. Inform., pp. 11:1–11:14, Schloss Dagstuhl-Leibniz-Zentrum fuer Informatik, Dagstuhl, Germany, 2016, doi:10.4230/LIPIcs.STACS.2016.11, URL https://drops.dagstuhl.de/opus/volltexte/2016/5712/.
- V. Kozyakin, The Berger-Wang formula for the Markovian joint spectral radius, Linear Algebra Appl., 448 (2014), 315-328, doi:10.1016/j.laa.2014.01.022, URL https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0024379514000408, arXiv:1401.2711.
- R. Cross and V. Kozyakin, Double exponential instability of triangular arbitrage systems, Discrete Contin. Dyn. Syst. Ser. B, 18 (2013), 349-376, doi:10.3934/dcdsb.2013.18.349, URL https://www.aimsciences.org/article/doi/10.3934/dcdsb.2013.18.349, arXiv:1204.3422.
- V. Kozyakin, An explicit Lipschitz constant for the joint spectral radius, Linear Algebra Appl., 433 (2010), 12-18, doi:10.1016/j.laa.2010.01.028, URL https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0024379510000418, arXiv:0909.3170.
- V. Kozyakin, Iterative building of Barabanov norms and computation of the joint spectral radius for matrix sets, Discrete Contin. Dyn. Syst. Ser. B, 14 (2010), 143-158, doi: 10.3934/dcdsb.2010.14.143, URL https://www.aimsciences.org/article/doi/10.3934/dcdsb.2010.14.143, arXiv:0810.2154.
- V. Kozyakin, Polynomial reformulation of the Kuo criteria for V-sufficiency of mapgerms, Discrete Contin. Dyn. Syst. Ser. B, 14 (2010), 587-602, doi:10.3934/dcdsb.2010.14.587, URL https://www.aimsciences.org/article/doi/10.3934/dcdsb.2010.14.587, arXiv:0907.0571.
- V. Kozyakin, On accuracy of approximation of the spectral radius by the Gelfand formula, Linear Algebra Appl., 431 (2009), 2134-2141, doi:10.1016/j.laa.2009.07.008, URL https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0024379509003590, arXiv:0810.2856.
- V. Kozyakin, A. Krasnosel'skii and D. Rachinskii, Asymptotics of the Arnold tongues in problems at infinity, Discrete Contin. Dyn. Syst., **20** (2008), 989-1011, doi: 10.3934/dcds.2008.20.989, URL https://www.aimsciences.org/article/doi/10.3934/dcds.2008.20.989.
- V. Kozyakin, Structure of extremal trajectories of discrete linear systems and the finiteness conjecture, Autom. Remote Control, 68 (2007), 174–209, doi:

- 10.1134/S0005117906040171, URL https://link.springer.com/article/10.1134/S0005117906040171.
- V. Kozyakin, A dynamical systems construction of a counterexample to the finiteness conjecture, in: Proceedings of the 44th IEEE Conference on Decision and Control, 2005 and 2005 European Control Conference. CDC-ECC'05., pp. 2338-2343, 2005, doi:10.1109/CDC.2005.1582511, URL https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/1582511.
- V. Kozyakin, A. Bhaya and E. Kaszkurewicz, *A global asymptotic stability result for a class of totally asynchronous discrete nonlinear systems*, Math. Control Signals Systems, **12** (1999), 143–166, doi:10.1007/PL00009848, URL https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/PL00009848.
- A. Bhaya, E. Kaszkurewicz and V. Kozyakin, Existence and stability of a unique equilibrium in continuous-valued discrete-time asynchronous Hopfield neural networks, IEEE Trans. Neural Netw., 7 (1996), 620-628, doi:10.1109/72.501720, URL https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/501720.
- V. Kozyakin, Algebraic unsolvability of problem of absolute stability of desynchronized systems, Autom. Remote Control, **51** (1990), 754–759.